<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-20T11:43:39+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">MINNE lab</title><subtitle>MINNE lab: Research in biomedical imaging and deep learning</subtitle><entry><title type="html">First International Society of Tractography conference</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/10/16/IST-conference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First International Society of Tractography conference" /><published>2025-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/10/16/IST-conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/10/16/IST-conference.html"><![CDATA[<p>Our group was represented by <a href="/people/sanna">Sanna Persson</a> and <a href="/people/rodrigo">Rodrigo Moreno</a> at the first International Society of Tractography conference. We presented an abstract here with a power pitch showcasing our research contributions to the tractography community.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/ist-conference/IST_org.PNG" alt="IST conference" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our group was represented by Sanna Persson and Rodrigo Moreno at the first International Society of Tractography conference. We presented an abstract here with a power pitch showcasing our research contributions to the tractography community.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/ist-conference/IST_org.PNG" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/ist-conference/IST_org.PNG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">MINNELab at MICCAI 2025 — Reconnecting with the Community in Daejeon 🇰🇷</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/10/11/MICCAI-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MINNELab at MICCAI 2025 — Reconnecting with the Community in Daejeon 🇰🇷" /><published>2025-10-11T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-10-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/10/11/MICCAI-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/10/11/MICCAI-2025.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/miccai-2025/MICCAI.png" alt="Minnelab at MICCAI 2025" /></p>

<p>This year, some members of <strong>MINNELab</strong> had the pleasure of attending <strong>MICCAI 2025</strong> in <strong>Daejeon, South Korea</strong> — an incredible experience to reconnect with the vibrant and inspiring <strong>MICCAI community</strong>. The conference provided a fantastic opportunity for discussions, collaborations, and the exchange of ideas across medical imaging and AI.</p>

<p><a href="/people/simone"><strong>Simone Bendazzoli</strong></a> presented at two workshops:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>BraTS Workshop</strong> — <em>BraTS-FL: Enhancing Generalization in Brain Tumor Segmentation via Federated Learning</em>
This work introduced a federated learning approach to improve <strong>generalization across brain tumor subtypes</strong>, including adult glioma, metastasis, meningioma, pediatric glioma, and sub-Saharan African cohorts. The paper will appear soon in the workshop proceedings.<br />
The method was also <strong>awarded first prize</strong> in the <strong>BraTS GoaT Task 7 subchallenge</strong> on generalizability across tumor types — a rewarding recognition for the effort toward creating more robust and inclusive AI models in neuroimaging.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>DeCaF (Distributed and Collaborative Federated Learning) 2025 Workshop</strong> — <em>MONet-FL: Extending nnU-Net with MONAI for Clinical Federated Learning</em><br />
Simone presented the <strong>MONet Bundle</strong>, an open-source framework that integrates <strong>nnU-Net</strong> into the <strong>MONAI ecosystem</strong>, enabling its use in <strong>federated learning, active learning</strong>, and <strong>PACS integration</strong>.<br />
The MONet Bundle was showcased in two federated tasks: <strong>whole-body PET-CT lymphoma segmentation</strong> and <strong>multimodal MRI brain tumor segmentation</strong>.</p>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-032-05663-4_10">Paper (Springer Link)</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://github.com/minnelab/MONet-Bundle">Code (GitHub)</a></li>
      <li>A dedicated post about the <strong>MONet Bundle</strong> will be available soon.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Beyond the scientific exchange, the team deeply appreciated the <strong>warm hospitality and rich culture of Korea</strong>, from the food and traditions to the welcoming atmosphere throughout Daejeon.</p>

<p>We return from MICCAI 2025 energized and inspired — looking forward to <strong>reconnecting with the MICCAI community</strong> soon for more exciting discussions, collaborations, and innovations in medical imaging AI.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/miccai-2025/MICCAI.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/miccai-2025/MICCAI.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Study trip to LA organized by WASP</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/10/04/WASP-LA-trip.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Study trip to LA organized by WASP" /><published>2025-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/10/04/WASP-LA-trip</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/10/04/WASP-LA-trip.html"><![CDATA[<p>Our group was represented by <a href="/people/sanna">Sanna Persson</a> as WASP affilited at an exciting study trip to Los Angeles organized by WASP (Wallenberg AI, Autonomous Systems and Software Program). The trip provided valuable opportunities to visit prestigious universities and leading technology companies in the LA area.</p>

<h2 id="university-visits">University Visits</h2>

<h3 id="uc-irvine">UC Irvine</h3>
<p>We had the privilege of visiting UC Irvine, where we engaged with faculty and researchers working on cutting-edge AI and autonomous systems research.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/la-2025/uc-irvine.jpeg" alt="UC Irvine Campus" />
<em>The beautiful UC Irvine campus, where we met with researchers working on AI and autonomous systems.</em></p>

<h2 id="company-visits">Company Visits</h2>

<h3 id="nasa-jet-propulsion-laboratory">NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory</h3>
<p>One of the highlights of the trip was our visit to NASA’s Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL), where we got an inside look at some of the most advanced robotics and space technology in the world.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/la-2025/nasa-robot.JPG" alt="NASA Robot" />
<em>Exploring advanced robotics technology at NASA’s Jet Propulsion Laboratory.</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/la-2025/nasa.jpg" alt="NASA Facility" />
<em>The impressive NASA JPL facility, home to groundbreaking space exploration technology.</em></p>

<h2 id="la-experience">LA Experience</h2>
<p>Beyond the academic and professional visits, we also had the chance to experience the unique atmosphere of Los Angeles.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/la-2025/palms.JPG" alt="LA Palms" /></p>

<p>This study trip was an excellent opportunity to network with researchers and professionals in the field, learn about the latest developments in AI and autonomous systems, and gain insights into how these technologies are being applied in both academic and industrial settings.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our group was represented by Sanna Persson as WASP affilited at an exciting study trip to Los Angeles organized by WASP (Wallenberg AI, Autonomous Systems and Software Program). The trip provided valuable opportunities to visit prestigious universities and leading technology companies in the LA area.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/la-2025/uc-irvine.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/la-2025/uc-irvine.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">MAIA at AIDA TechDays Workshop</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/09/17/MAIA-AIDA-WorkShop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MAIA at AIDA TechDays Workshop" /><published>2025-09-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-09-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/09/17/MAIA-AIDA-WorkShop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/09/17/MAIA-AIDA-WorkShop.html"><![CDATA[<p>On <strong>17 September 2025</strong>, <a href="/people/simone"><strong>Simone Bendazzoli</strong></a> presented <a href="/maia/"><strong>MAIA</strong></a> at the <strong>AIDA TechDays Workshop</strong>, hosted by the <strong>AIDA community</strong>, Sweden’s leading arena for medical AI research. This workshop showcased <strong>MAIA’s capabilities</strong> in facilitating collaborative, reproducible, and scalable AI development in healthcare.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/maia-aida-techdays.png" alt="Minnelab at MICCAI 2025" /></p>
<h3 id="workshop-highlights">Workshop Highlights</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://minnelab.github.io/MAIA-AIDA-TechDays-Workshop/#/9"><strong>End-to-End Model Development</strong></a>: Demonstrated the workflow from DICOM data ingestion to model deployment using <strong>nnU-Net</strong> within the MAIA platform.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://minnelab.github.io/MAIA-AIDA-TechDays-Workshop/#/47"><strong>Active Learning Integration</strong></a>: Showcased how <strong>MONAI Label</strong> and <strong>3D Slicer</strong> can be utilized for active learning cycles, enhancing model performance with minimal labeled data.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://minnelab.github.io/MAIA-AIDA-TechDays-Workshop/#/52"><strong>Federated Learning Implementation</strong></a>: Explained the setup of <strong>NVFlare</strong> within MAIA for federated learning, enabling collaborative model training across institutions without sharing sensitive data.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="-access-workshop-materials">🔗 Access Workshop Materials</h3>

<p>All workshop materials, including slides, Jupyter notebooks, and setup guides, are available on the <a href="https://minnelab.github.io/MAIA-AIDA-TechDays-Workshop">MAIA-AIDA TechDays Workshop page</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On 17 September 2025, Simone Bendazzoli presented MAIA at the AIDA TechDays Workshop, hosted by the AIDA community, Sweden’s leading arena for medical AI research. This workshop showcased MAIA’s capabilities in facilitating collaborative, reproducible, and scalable AI development in healthcare.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/maia-aida-techdays.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/maia-aida-techdays.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Decomposing the effect of normal aging and Alzheimer’s disease in brain morphological changes via learned aging templates</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/04/07/paper_decomposing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decomposing the effect of normal aging and Alzheimer’s disease in brain morphological changes via learned aging templates" /><published>2025-04-07T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/04/07/paper_decomposing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/04/07/paper_decomposing.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Published in Scientific Reports</strong></p>

<p>Paper link: <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-025-96234-w">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-025-96234-w</a></p>

<p>Code repository: <a href="https://github.com/Fjr9516/DBM_with_DL">https://github.com/Fjr9516/DBM_with_DL</a></p>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Alzheimer’s disease (AD) subjects usually show more profound morphological changes with time compared to cognitively normal (CN) individuals. These changes are the combination of two major biological processes: normal aging and AD pathology. Investigating normal aging and residual morphological changes separately can increase our understanding of the disease. This paper proposes two scores, the aging score (AS) and the AD-specific score (ADS), whose purpose is to measure these two components of brain atrophy independently. For this, in the first step, we estimate the atrophy due to the normal aging of CN subjects by computing the expected deformation required to match imaging templates generated at different ages. We used a state-of-the-art generative deep learning model for generating such imaging templates. In the second step, we apply deep learning-based diffeomorphic registration to align the given image of a subject with a reference imaging template. Parametrization of this deformation field is then decomposed voxel-wise into their parallel and perpendicular components with respect to the parametrization of the expected atrophy of CN individuals in one year computed in the first step. AS and ADS are the normalized scores of these two components, respectively. We evaluated these two scores on the OASIS-3 dataset with 1,014 T1-weighted MRI scans. Of these, 326 scans were from CN subjects, and 688 scans were from subjects diagnosed with AD at various stages of clinical severity, as defined by clinical dementia rating (CDR) scores. Our results reveal that AD is marked by both disease-specific brain changes and an accelerated aging process. Such changes affect brain regions differently. Moreover, the proposed scores were sensitive to detect changes in the early stages of the disease, which is promising for its potential future use in clinical studies. Our code is freely available at <a href="https://github.com/Fjr9516/DBM_with_DL">https://github.com/Fjr9516/DBM_with_DL</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jingru Fu, Daniel Ferreira, Örjan Smedby &amp; Rodrigo Moreno</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Published in Scientific Reports]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/papers/decomposing_paper.png.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/papers/decomposing_paper.png.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">MICCAI Conference 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/10/miccai-conference-2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MICCAI Conference 2024" /><published>2024-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/10/miccai-conference-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/10/miccai-conference-2024.html"><![CDATA[<p>We are excited to announce that our lab is visiting the MICCAI (Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention) conference! This prestigious event brings together researchers from around the world to share the latest advances in medical image computing and computer-assisted intervention.</p>

<p>We were represented by Fabian, Simone, Sanna, and Zhikai, and presented in the CDMRI workshop, DeepBReath, and BraTS.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are excited to announce that our lab is visiting the MICCAI (Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention) conference! This prestigious event brings together researchers from around the world to share the latest advances in medical image computing and computer-assisted intervention.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/miccai-2025/MICCAI.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/miccai-2025/MICCAI.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bounding tractogram redundancy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/23/bounding-tractograms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bounding tractogram redundancy" /><published>2024-07-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-07-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/07/23/bounding-tractograms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/23/bounding-tractograms.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Published in Frontiers in Neuroscience</strong></p>

<p>Paper link: <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnins.2024.1403804/full">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnins.2024.1403804/full</a></p>

<p>Introduction: In tractography, redundancy poses a significant challenge, often resulting in tractograms that include anatomically implausible streamlines or those that fail to represent the brain’s white matter architecture accurately. Current filtering methods aim to refine tractograms by addressing these issues, but they lack a unified measure of redundancy and can be computationally demanding.</p>

<p>Methods: We propose a novel framework to quantify tractogram redundancy based on filtering tractogram subsets without endorsing a specific filtering algorithm. Our approach defines redundancy based on the anatomical plausibility and diffusion signal representation of streamlines, establishing both lower and upper bounds for the number of false-positive streamlines and the tractogram redundancy.</p>

<p>Results: We applied this framework to tractograms from the Human Connectome Project, using geometrical plausibility and statistical methods informed by the streamlined attributes and ensemble consensus. Our results establish bounds for the tractogram redundancy and the false-discovery rate of the tractograms.</p>

<p>Conclusion: This study advances the understanding of tractogram redundancy and supports the refinement of tractography methods. Future research will focus on further validating the proposed framework and exploring tractogram compression possibilities.</p>]]></content><author><name>Sanna Persson &amp; Rodrigo Moreno</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Published in Frontiers in Neuroscience]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/papers/bounding_tractography.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/papers/bounding_tractography.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>